okay let's try a question
relating to spontaneity consider the
conversion of limestone to lime so we
have calcium carbonate caco3 yielding
calcium oxide CA o and co2 gas the
values of Delta H and Delta S are 179
point 1 kilojoules per mole and 160
point 2 joules per Kelvin respectively
at 298 K and 1 bar assuming that these
values do not change with temperature
what is the temperature above which
conversion of limestone to lime will be
spontaneous so we need to know some
things about Gibbs free energy enthalpy
entropy we need to know how those values
correlate we need to know something
about the conditions within which a
reaction will be spontaneous so go ahead
and check out my tutorial on Gibbs free
energy if you need some review and when
you're ready give it a try
so the first
thing we have to remember is that
reactions are spontaneous when Delta G
is less than zero so we need Delta G to
be negative in order for a reaction to
be spontaneous so if we have Delta G
equals Delta H minus T Delta s and we
need Delta G to be less than zero then
we also need Delta H minus T Delta s to
be less than zero because those are
equivalent now because we're trying to
figure out the temperature above which
conversion of limestone to lime will be
spontaneous that means we're going to be
solving for a temperature so let's
rearrange this inequality to solve for
temperature all we do is add T Delta s
to both sides and then divide by Delta s
and we get T is greater than Delta H
over Delta S so we can just go ahead and
plug in the
use that we know now we have 179.1
kilojoules per mole for Delta H but our
entropy value has joules so these are
gonna need to agree let's just go ahead
and multiply this one by a thousand that
way we'll have it in joules so one
hundred and seventy-nine thousand one
hundred joules per mole and then we can
divide that by a hundred and sixty point
two joules per Kelvin that way the
joules will cancel and we end up with
1118 Kelvin so that means that despite
the enthalpic unfavorability we see that
this is endothermic right one hundred
seventy nine point one kilojoules per
mole this is an endothermic reaction
which we typically expect to not be
spontaneous however it is entropically
favorable we're producing more
substances we're producing a gas
therefore if we raise the temperature
high enough that T Delta s term will
outweigh the Delta H term and it happens
to be this value 1118 Kelvin above that
temperature this will be a spontaneous process.